Yassine Laguel's Resume

CONTACT INFORMATION

Laboratoire Jean Alexandre Dieudonné

Université Côte d'Azur

28 avenue Valrose,

Mail: yassine.laguel@univ-cotedazur.fr
https://yassine-laguel.github.io

Phone: +33-745030188

Nice, 06108, France

RESEARCH INTERESTS My interests center around optimization under uncertainty and its applications to stochastic programming and machine learning. A common thread in my research is the design and analysis of numerical algorithms to address risk in data-driven applications. I draw and extend ideas and tools from convex optimization, probability theory and numerical analysis while keeping an *operational* approach, with a balance between theoretical and practical contributions.

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

Université Côte d'Azur,

Sep 2023 - Present

Associate Professor.

Nice, France.

Rutgers University,

Jan 2022 - June 2023

Postdoctoral Associate at the Department of Management Sciences and Information Systems (MSIS), hosted by Prof. Mert Gürbüzbalaban.

New Brunswick, USA.

Princeton University,

Fall 2022

Departmental Guest at the Center for Statistics and Machine Learning (CSML).

Princeton, USA.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Optimization and Machine Learning.

Oct 2018 - Nov 2021

Supervised by Jérôme Malick, Université Grenoble Alpes, Grenoble, France.

B.S., M.S. in Computer Sciences and Applied Mathematics

Sep 2015 - Sep 2018

Diplôme d'ingénieur from ENSIMAG, Grenoble France.

B.S., M.S. in Mathematics

Sep 2015 - Sep 2018

Master major in statistics, Université Grenoble Alpes, Grenoble, France. Degrees pursued in parallel to my diplôme d'ingénieur.

JOURNAL PAPERS

- [1] **Yassine Laguel**, Mert Gürbüzbalaban, Necdet Serhat Aybat. High probability and riskaverse guarantees for stochastic saddle point problems. Accepted in the Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR). 2024 https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/risk-averse-minimax.pdf
- [2] **Yassine Laguel**, Wim Van Ackooij, Jérôme Malick. Chance constrained problems: a bilevel convex optimization perspective. *Computational Optimization and Applications*. 2024. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/taco-paper.pdf
- [3] Yu-Guan Hsieh, **Yassine Laguel**, Franck Iutzeler, Jérôme Malick. Push–pull with device sampling. *IEEE Transactions in Automatic Control*. 2023. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/ppds-paper.pdf
- [4] **Yassine Laguel**, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Federated learning with heterogeneous data: a superquantile optimization approach. *Machine Learning Journal*. 2023. https://arxiv.org/pdf/2112.09429.pdf

- [5] Yassine Laguel. Risk-averse optimization: models, algorithms, and applications in machine learning. *Ph.D. Dissertation*. 2022. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/phd_thesis.pdf
- [6] Yassine Laguel, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Superquantile-based learning: a direct approach using gradient-based optimization. *Journal of Signal Processing Systems*. No. 94, pages 161–177. 2022. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/2021_jsps.pdf
- [7] **Yassine Laguel**, Wim Van Ackooij, Jérôme Malick, Guilherme Matiussi Ramalho. On the convexity of level-sets of probability functions. *Journal of Convex Analysis*. No. 29.2, pages 411-442. 2022. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/files/transconcavity-paper.pdf
- [8] Yassine Laguel, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Superquantiles at work: machine learning applications and efficient (sub)gradient computation. Set-Valued and Variational Analysis. No. 29, pages 967–996. 2022. https://yassine-laguel. github.io/files/svaa-paper.pdf.
- [9] Gilles Bareilles, Yassine Laguel, Dmitry Grishchenko, Franck Iutzeler, Jerome Malick. Randomized progressive hedging methods for multi-stage stochastic programming. *Annals of Operations Research*. No. 295, pages 535–560. 2020. https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.12186

CONFERENCE PAPERS

- [10] Yassine Laguel, Yasa Syed, Necdet Serhat Aybat, Mert Gürbüzbalaban. High-probability complexity guarantees for nonconvex minimax problems. Neurips 2024 https://arxiv. org/pdf/2405.14130
- [11] Yassine Laguel, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Tackling Distribution Shifts in Federated Learning with Superquantile Aggregation. NeurIPS 2022 Workshop on Distribution Shifts: Connecting Methods and Applications. Spotlight paper. 2022.
- [12] **Yassine Laguel**, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Differentially Private Federated Quantiles with the Distributed Discrete Gaussian Mechanism. *International Workshop on Federated Learning: Recent Advances and New Challenges*. 2022.
- [13] Yassine Laguel, Krishna Pillutla, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. Device heterogeneity in federated learning: a superquantile approach. Proceedings of the 55th Annual Conference on Information Sciences and Systems (CISS 2021). https://arxiv.org/abs/2002. 11223
- [14] Yassine Laguel, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. First order optimization for superquantile-based supervised learning. Proceedings of the Machine Learning and Signal Processing Conference (MLSP 2020) Best Student Paper Award. https://arxiv.org/abs/2009. 14575

SOFTWARE TACO 2022

Python toolbox for chance constrained optimization. Yassine Laguel, Wim Van Ackooij, Jérôme Malick. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/taco/.

SPQR 2020

Python toolbox for superquantile minimization. Yassine Laguel, Jérôme Malick, Zaid Harchaoui. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/spqr/.

RandomizedProgressiveHedging.jl

2019

Julia toolbox for solving multistage stochastic problems by randomized versions of the progressive hedging algorithm. Gilles Bareilles, Yassine Laguel, Dmitry Grishchenko, Franck Iutzeler, Jerome Malick. https://yassine-laguel.github.io/RandomizedProgressiveHedging.jl/stable.

Invited Talks	 On the acceleration/robustness trade-off for stochastic min-max problems 55th Journées des Statistiques High probability and risk-averse guarantees for stochastic saddle point problems 	2024
	 Talk. Bordeaux, France. Université Versailles Saint-Quentin High probability and risk-averse guarantees for stochastic saddle point problems Talk. Versailles, France. 	2024
	 Université Avignon High probability and risk-averse guarantees for stochastic saddle point problems 	2024
	 Talk. Avignon, France. Telecom Paris Robustness for Models and Algorithms in Machine Learning Talk. Scalar, France. 	2023
	 Talk. Saclay, France. Laboratoire Jean Alexandre Dieudonné Robustness for Models and Algorithms in Machine Learning Talk. Nice. France. 	2023
	 Talk. Nice, France. Institut Montpelliérain Alexander Grothendieck Robustness for Models and Algorithms in Machine Learning Talk. Mantaellier France. 	2022
	 Talk. Montpellier, France. INFORMS annual meeting A robust perspective on acceleration for saddle point problems 	2022
	 Talk. Indianapolis, USA. International conference on continuous optimization (ICCOPT) New perspectives on robustness via the Conditional Value at Risk. Talk. Lehigh, USA. 	2022
	Handling statistical heterogeneity in federated learning	
	 Magnet Seminar Federated learning with heterogeneous data: a superquantile optimization approach Talk. Inria Lille, France. 	2022 h.
	• University of Washington Machine Learning Seminar Convex risk measures: models, algorithms and applications in federated learning. Talk. Seattle, USA.	2022
	• Thoth Seminar Convex risk measures: models, algorithms and applications in federated learning. Talk. Inria Grenoble, France.	2022
	• Journées des Statistiques Risk-sensitive learning for heterogeneous frameworks. Talk. Nice, France.	2021
	Workshop on Communication Efficient Distributed Optimization Device heterogeneity in federated learning: a superquantile approach. Poster Online workshop.	2021
	 Federated Learning One World Seminar Device heterogeneity in federated learning: a superquantile approach. Talk. Online Seminar. 	2020
	https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W-oNzU04Y8I • Optimization for Machine Learning Conference Handling device heterogeneity in federated learning. *Poster. Marseille, France.	2020
	PhD. Defense	2021
	Risk-averse optimization: models, algorithms, and applications in machine learning. <i>Talk</i> . Grenoble, France.	

Hidden convexity in probabilistic programming

	ANSI Seminar On hidden convexity in chance constrained problems. This is a series of the convexity of the constrained problems.	2021
	 Talk. Los Alamos, USA. SMAI-MODE Conference A DC approach for chance constraints. Talk. Saclay, France. 	2020
	https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KB3sV-trEy4&list • International conference on continuous optimization (ICCOPT) On the interplay between generalized concavity and chance constraints. Talk. Berlin, Germany.	2019
	 Efficient oracles for distributionally robust optimization IFDS Workshop on Distributional Robustness in Data Science SPQR: A Toolbox for Superquantile-based Learning Talk. Seattle, USA. 	2022
	 Machine Learning and Signal Processing Conference (MLSP) First-order optimization for superquantile-based supervised learning. Best student Paper Award. Talk. Espoo, Finland. 	2020
	https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JRWvWxOxRiQ • ROADEF Practical minimization of CVar-based risk functions.	2020
	 Talk. Montpellier, France. International conference on stochastic programming (ICSP) 1st-order methods for minimization of superquantile-based risk measures. Talk. Trondheim, Norway. 	2019
Teaching Experience	Instructor	
EALENEE	 Introduction to measure theory and probability. Université Côte d'Azur. Undergraduate Course. Nice, France. 	48h.
	• Introduction to numerical optimization. Université Côte d'Azur. <i>Undergraduate Course</i> . Nice, France.	8h.
	• Fundamentals of analysis and algebra. Grenoble INP. <i>Undergraduate Course</i> . Grenoble, France.	37.5h.
	 Fundamentals of analysis and algebra. Unversité Grenoble Alpes. <i>Undergraduate Course</i>. Grenoble, France. Introduction to R. 	36h. 2x30h.
	Université Grenoble Alpes. <i>Undergraduate Course</i> . Grenoble, France. • Introduction to Python.	2x30h.
	 Université Grenoble Alpes. <i>Graduate Course</i>. Grenoble, France. Convex and distributed optimization. Université Grenoble Alpes. <i>Graduate Course</i>. Grenoble, France. 	18h.
	• Numerical optimization. ENSIMAG. <i>Graduate Course</i> . Grenoble, France.	25h.
	Guest Lecturer	
	 Introduction to risk-sensitive learning. University de Tlemcem. Graduate Course. Tlemcen, Algeria. 	4h.
	 Distributionally robust machine learning. 	4h.
	 University of Washington. <i>Graduate Course</i>. Seattle, USA. Introduction to federated learning. ENSIMAG. <i>Graduate Course</i>. Grenoble, France. 	1.5h.

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

Committee Service

- Co-organizer of the Probability and Statistics Seminar at Université Côte d'Azur, since Mar. 2024.
- Founder and Organizer of the Optim & ML Seminar at Rutgers University, from Mar. 2022 to Jun. 2023.
- Founder and Organizer of GORGeous (Grenoble Optimization Reading Group), at the Université Grenoble Alpes, from Sep. 2019 to Oct. 2021. https://sites.google.com/view/gorgeous-optim/
- Jury member for the International Tournament of Young Mathematicians (ITYM).
 Iasi, Romania. 2013.

Referee Service

- Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR)
- Mathematics of Operations Research
- EURO Journal on Computational Optimization
- Automatica
- Optimization
- Journal of Optimization Theory and Applications (JOTA)

Conference Service

- Program Committee: 53rd International Conference on Parallel Processing (ICPP 2024).
- Program Committee: 51st International Conference on Parallel Processing (ICPP 2022).
- Organizer of the session First-order methods for min-max problems at ICCOPT 2022.
- Organizer of the session First-order methods for minimax problems at INFORMS 2022.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Research Internships

• University of Washington, Seattle, USA.
Initiated the series of works [6, 8, 10, 11].

• EDF R&D, Saclay, France. Led to the publication of the journal paper [7]. 2017.

2018

WeSave, Financial Startup in Paris, France.
 Worked on the establishment of quantitative criterion based on random correlations matrices to predict crises.

Consulting Activity

2016

Conception and development of a transport management software for an international firm.

AWARDS Spotlight Paper

2022

NeurIPS 2022 Workshop on Distribution Shifts: Connecting Methods and Applications. New Orleans, USA.

Best Student Paper Award

2020

2012

2012

Machine learning and signal processing conference (MLSP 2020). Espoo, Finland.

Finalist of the International Tournament of Young Mathematicians (ITYM)

 $Rank: 3^{rd}$. Orsay, France.

Winner of the French Tournament of Young Mathematicians (TFJM)

Saclay, France.